<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A parallel wherein it appears that the Socinian agrees with the papist, if not exceeds him in idolatry, antiscripturism and fanaticism / by Francis Fullwood ...</title>
            <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2513</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38752</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18110184</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18110184</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106798</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40718)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106798)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1124:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A parallel wherein it appears that the Socinian agrees with the papist, if not exceeds him in idolatry, antiscripturism and fanaticism / by Francis Fullwood ...</title>
                  <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. and J. Churchill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Socinianism.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106798:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106798:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PARALLEL: Wherein it appears, that the SOCINIAN Agrees with the PAPIST, If not exceeds him in <hi>Idolatry, Antiſcripturiſm</hi> and <hi>Fanaticiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>FRANCIS F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LLWOOD,</hi> D. D. and Arch-deacon of <hi>Totneſs</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Thinkeſt thou this O man, that judgeſt them which do ſuch things, and doſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape,</hi> 
               <bibl>Rom. 2. 3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Happy is he, that condemneth not himſelf in that thing which he alloweth,</hi> 
               <bibl>Rom. 14. 22.</bibl>
            </q>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>May</hi> 16. 1693.</date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <signed>R. Barker.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>J. Churchill,</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row.</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106798:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106798:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE Moſt Reverend Father in God, JOHN LORD Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>And Primate of all</hi> ENGLAND. FRANCIS F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LLWOOD</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Preſumes with all Humility, to Dedicate this following ſhort Diſcourſe, touching</hi> Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT would be an unpardonable vanity in me, to imagine, either that the World needed my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, how <hi>Seaſonable</hi> and highly <hi>Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> His GRACE's late <hi>Vindication</hi> of our Lord's <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation</hi> was, or, my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation</hi> of it, could I find words worthy to do it.</p>
            <p>Yet thus much I cannot forbear to utter, that 'tis a <hi>Rare</hi> thing to find ſuch <hi>Condeſcention,</hi> ſuch <hi>Candour</hi> and ſuch <hi>Charity</hi> even towards the <hi>Enemies</hi> of our Common Faith, as well as to <hi>Friends</hi> of it, in a perſon of the <hi>Higheſt Station:</hi> Whereby, indeed he ſhews himſelf forth, as an
<pb facs="tcp:106798:3"/> Eminent <hi>Head,</hi> not only Adorning, but Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and <hi>Animating</hi> by an admirable example, the great <hi>Body</hi> of our Church under him.</p>
            <p>If I may preſume to ſpeak my mind in a few words more; the ſtrength of <hi>Reaſon</hi> is ſo dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouſly managed in thoſe four Excellent and Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Sermons,</hi> that it will not be eaſie to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them, the two former of them have driven, both the <hi>Arian</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> Reaſon, to palpable <hi>Non-ſence:</hi> And the Two latter, have given the World ſo reaſonable and ſatisfactory account of the Chriſtian Oeconomy, that all their idle <hi>Ideas</hi> and imaginary pretences to the contrary, are <hi>Deaded at the Root,</hi> and put to ſilence in the <hi>Grave</hi> without hope of a <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> at leaſt, in <hi>the ſame Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The World is a ſenſible Witneſs of the truth of this, to which I was provoked by the ſtrange aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſome amongst us, having no farther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in it then the Publick advantage; no, not ſo much as to gain his GRACE's Countenance and <hi>Protection</hi> of this ſmall <hi>Pamphlet</hi> (the uſual pretence of ſuch <hi>Dedications:)</hi> But I moſt humbly beg His GRACE's pardon for the boldneſs of it: and pray heartily, that GOD would long preſerve His <hi>Perſon</hi> and ſucceed all His Excellent <hi>Endeavours,</hi> in the Government, and for the good of this <hi>Poor Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Litton <hi>near</hi> Dorcheſter, <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 25. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106798:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>VVHAT I have charged the <hi>Socinians</hi> with, <hi>viz</hi> That they are <hi>equally</hi> guilty of <hi>Idolatry, Antiſcripturiſm,</hi> and <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> with the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> if not more hainouſly; is no more then what their Learned Adverſaries do generally <hi>twit</hi> them with. They have indeed done it <hi>obitèr,</hi> or more by the by, and I have more largely undertaken to prove it upon them in the following Sheets.</p>
            <p>The <hi>SOCINIAN</hi> ſtands Indited here of thoſe three great <hi>Offences</hi> in Religion; and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks 'tis but reaſonable to expect, he ſhould anſwer to this Charge before he proceeds any farther to diſturb our <hi>Common Faith,</hi> with his novel and nice Diſputes and Quarrels about particular Points.</p>
            <p>If he think himſelf concern'd ſo to do, I would adviſe him to begin with the <hi>Firſt</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Inditement, and clear himſelf and
<pb facs="tcp:106798:4"/> his <hi>Cauſe</hi> from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> in the ſence, we charge it upon the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More plainly, That he would Conſider and <hi>Speak out</hi> unto theſe two Propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> 'That to give the Worſhip due to the <hi>Supream God</hi> to a <hi>Creature</hi> is <hi>Idolatry. 2ly.</hi> That 'tis Lawful and therefore no <hi>Idolatry,</hi> to give the Worſhip due to the Supream God to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe two Propoſitions divide the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as they call themſelves into Two <hi>Parties:</hi> One of them affirms the Firſt, and the other the Second, as I have obſerved; and in my Opinion, both of them do their parts againſt each other unanſwerably: And if both be found ſo far in the right, I hope neither of them will ſee Cauſe to deny the <hi>Concluſion; That then Jeſus Chriſt is more then a mere Creature,</hi> that is, the <hi>ſame with the Supream God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, if any think themſelves engag'd to perſiſt in the denial of either of thoſe Two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, for the ſaving of their Cauſe, when we hear what they can ſay, I doubt not, but they will have a farther and a fuller Anſwer if need be. The <hi>Good Spirit lead us into all Truth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:106798:4"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Deſign Stated and brought to an Iſſue.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>SOCINIAN</hi> values himſelf much for his Oppoſition to <hi>Popery;</hi> and indeed ſome of that Name, have managed it in many conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Articles,</hi> with great Reaſon and Merit; and were I ſuch an <hi>Unitarian,</hi> as he pretends to be, I ſhould eſteem it more agreeable and leſs Scandalous to be called a <hi>Jew,</hi> or a <hi>Turk,</hi> or an <hi>Infidel,</hi> than ſo bad a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> as the <hi>Papiſt</hi> is.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Socinian</hi> hath one very dear and darling Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and is a Man of ſo much Reaſon and Reſolution, that if Reaſon in the Service of his <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> require it, he ſeems not to ſtick at any thing, tho' it ſavour never ſo rankly even of <hi>Popery</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Yea, tho' the things themſelves abſtractedly conſidered, are the Objects of his profeſſed Hatred and Deteſtation: And though they bear the burthen of the <hi>Socinian</hi> charge againſt <hi>Popery;</hi> and tho' he upbraids the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> with ſome degrees of the ſame guilt; yet when the groſſeſt of thoſe things appear neceſſary for the Maintenance of his Cauſe, the <hi>Popery</hi> vaniſheth, the Oppoſition ceaſeth, and with great Friendſhip, the things otherwiſe deteſted, are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained and embraced, are openly profeſſed and practiced, and pleaded for, with all imaginable Reaſon and Zeal.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106798:5"/>
            <p> Now, That I may juſtifie what I have ſaid, 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, that there are three ſmall <hi>Peccadilloes,</hi> which lie pretty near the Root and Eſſence of the <hi>Papacy,</hi> in the Judgment of the <hi>Socinians</hi> themſelves, wherein (for the ſtate of their <hi>Cauſe</hi> no doubt) they do plainly Symbolize with, if not out-do the very <hi>Jeſuit.</hi> Theſe have reſpect to the <hi>Term</hi> of their Worſhip, the <hi>Rule</hi> of their Faith; And Laſtly, the very <hi>Foundation</hi> of their <hi>Religion,</hi> and are no leſs or greater than <hi>Idolatry, Antiſcripturiſm,</hi> and <hi>Fanatical Enthuſiaſm.</hi> In ſhort, my preſent charge upon the <hi>Socinian</hi> is this; that he agrees with, and even goes beyond the <hi>Papiſt</hi> in all theſe, viz. <hi>Idolatry, Antiſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turiſm</hi> and <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiaſm;</hi> all which, in the three <hi>Chapters</hi> following, I ſhall endeavour to prove and demonſtrate in a fair and juſt <hi>Compariſon</hi> betwixt them, which is all my preſent intention and buſineſs. For I muſt leave the <hi>Merits</hi> of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Cauſe at large, to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking promiſed by the Excellent and Learned Dean of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> who the World knows, will perform it through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and effectually, and earneſtly deſires and expects it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106798:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The</hi> Socinian <hi>compared with the</hi> Papiſt <hi>in point of</hi> Idolatry.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>THE Firſt Part of my deſigned Task is this, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the <hi>Socinian</hi> and <hi>Papiſt</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>Term</hi> of their Worſhip; to ſhew, wherein the <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> agrees with, and out-does the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> even in the point of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, 'tis evident, as well by the Light of <hi>Nature</hi> as <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> that the <hi>Secundo formale,</hi> the very Reaſon and Nature of <hi>Idolatry</hi> lies in this, the giving that Worſhip that is due to <hi>God</hi> alone, that is Divine and truly Religious Worſhip, to the <hi>Creature:</hi> And for this very reaſon, we charge the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> with the guilt of the horrid Sin of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Now, if the <hi>Socinian</hi> be found to profeſs and practice the ſame thing; that is, to give Divine and Religious Worſhip due to <hi>God</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a mere <hi>Creature</hi> in his own Judgment, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> is, it cannot be any breach of Charity or Juſtice, to charge him with the guilt of <hi>Idolatry</hi> in <hi>General,</hi> or in <hi>Special,</hi> with the ſame kind of <hi>Idolatry</hi> we charge upon the <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Papiſt,</hi> when he Worſhips the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> would excuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, becauſe he believes it to be <hi>God;</hi> yet the Learned Men of that Communion do acknowledge upon a Suppoſition, that there is no <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> of the Elements, ſuch Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> is at leaſt <hi>Material Idolatry:</hi> But how ſhall the <hi>Socinian</hi> be excuſed even from <hi>Formal Idolatry,</hi> tho' our <hi>Saviour</hi> be indeed <hi>God</hi> as he is, while they believe him to be but a <hi>Creature,</hi> and yet give him the Worſhip due to the <hi>Creator.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106798:6"/>
               <p> This is ſome aggravation, but more is added if we allow the <hi>Papiſt</hi>'s <hi>Diſtinction,</hi> of the kinds or degrees of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip proportionably to the various Objects of it. <hi>Doulia Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdoulia, &amp; Latria:</hi> the latter of which, they deny to any <hi>Creature,</hi> and count it peculiar to <hi>God</hi> alone: And tho' they believe, that the <hi>Mother</hi> of our Lord, hath ſo great Power with <hi>God,</hi> and over her <hi>Son;</hi> yet they ſay, that ſhe ought not to be Worſhipped with <hi>Latria,</hi> of the higheſt kind or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Worſhip: And their Learned Men affirm, that to give <hi>Latria</hi> to any Creature, is to be guilty of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, ſeeing the <hi>Papiſt</hi> do formally and Actually pay the ſame kind of Worſhip to Creatures, that is due to <hi>God,</hi> tho' different in <hi>Degree,</hi> as certainly they do, (call it by what name you pleaſe) their diſtinctions in <hi>Doctrine</hi> cannot acquit their <hi>Practice</hi> from <hi>Idolatry:</hi> For Religious Worſhip of the ſame <hi>Kind,</hi> with that which is due to <hi>God</hi> only, is <hi>Latria:</hi> and therefore, to give it to a <hi>Creature,</hi> muſt be <hi>Idolatry</hi> by their own <hi>Definitions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our <hi>Socinians</hi> are not ſo meal-mouth'd. They profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly in their very <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as well as Practice, they allow Divine Adoration and Worſhip truly Religious, that is <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria,</hi> to one; that, they ſay, is a mere Man. This they do, without <hi>Diſtinction</hi> or reſerve; and conſequently, their <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> is more abſolute, bare-fac'd and inexcuſable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> teacheth, that the <hi>Image</hi> of the Croſs may be Worſhipped with <hi>Latria.</hi> A very wild Propoſition; but he hath the ſlight to make the Worſhip of the <hi>Image</hi> to paſs through it, and the <hi>Croſs</hi> and our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and terminate in <hi>God:</hi> Yet we ſay his Doctrine is <hi>Idolatrous;</hi> do not the <hi>Socinians</hi> plead the ſame in effect, when ſome of them ſay, the Worſhip terminates in <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> which they equally pay to <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Subſtitute:</hi> But if they give Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to him, as a diſtinct Perſon and ſeparate Object from <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father;</hi> and affirm, that the ſame Honour is due to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is due to <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father;</hi> and that the Supream <hi>God</hi> hath given his own Glory to the <hi>Creature Chriſt:</hi> Is not their <hi>Idolatry</hi> more groſs and fulſome then the worſt of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106798:6"/>
               <p> In a word, our Learned Men have demonſtrated ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, that <hi>Popiſh Idolatry</hi> juſtifies the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Heathens.</hi> And in my obſervation, the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Socinians</hi> does not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly juſtifie but exceeds them both too and that of their Fathers, the <hi>Arians.</hi> To make this evident, I crave my Readers pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and pardon, while I make a little digreſſion; which yet I hope, he will not think impertinent to my main De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. Socinians <hi>greater</hi> Idolaters <hi>then</hi> Pagans <hi>or</hi> Arians.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Papiſt</hi> juſtifie <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolatry as much as they can, by giving Divine and Religious Worſhip, tho' they pretend 'tis in a lower degree, to Angels and dead Men; for the wiſer Heathen pretended the very ſame: They accounted their <hi>Daemons</hi> the Miniſters of God; ſecondary, Inferiour Gods; a middle ſort of Interceſſors, <hi>Dei facti:</hi> The Supream God, they ſaid, was the Maker of them: Whom therefore they ſtil'd <hi>Divum Pater,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Juſt as the <hi>Socinians</hi> term our Saviour; they ſay, they were Gods Deputies and Officers, to Govern under him. Conformably, as 'tis obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of <hi>Hierocles,</hi> theſe inferiour Gods were to be Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed indeed; yet but with an <hi>Inferior</hi> and middle kind of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, called <hi>Doulia:</hi> But the higher kind of Worſhip, or <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria,</hi> was due only to the <hi>Supream</hi> God: and they were ſo careful to maintain that Diſtinction, both with reſpect to the Objects, and the Worſhip, that Caution was given to the People (this is more I fear than the <hi>Papiſt</hi> do) not to give their inferiour Gods more Honour then was conſiſtent with the Dignity God had given them. <hi>Hieron.</hi> pag. 10.</p>
               <p>Doth not this Care and Caution uſed by the <hi>Pagans</hi> in their Idolatry reproach, condemn, and aggravate the more raſh and confuſed practice of <hi>Socinians?</hi> Theſe affirm boldly enough, that, tho' our Saviour is a <hi>meer</hi> Man, a <hi>dead</hi> Man, and only a God by Office, and not ſo by <hi>Nature;</hi> that is, a mere Creature, tho' Gods <hi>Subſtitute,</hi> yet they allow him equal Honour and Worſhip with the great God his Maker, without the niceneſs of diſtinction or limitation.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106798:7"/>
               <p> As for their Fathers the <hi>Arians,</hi> they might have learn'd the like Caution from them too. The Ancient <hi>Arians</hi> held Chriſt to be the great <hi>Gods Inſtrument,</hi> and not God himſelf: And upon this principle they perform'd to the Sacred Trinity <hi>Unequal Honours,</hi> as the Orthordox charged them, and they could by no means be perſwaded to Worſhip with equal Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Son and the Father; becauſe they believed <hi>Chriſt</hi> was but a Creature, or a made God. As <hi>Fulgent. Greg. Nyſſ.</hi> and <hi>Cyril. Alex.</hi> have obſerved. Now are not our <hi>Socinians</hi> much wiſer then their Parents? For, tho' they have far viler thoughts of the Perſon, Birth and Nature of Chriſt, than the <hi>Arians</hi> had, yet by what rule of proportion I know not, they allow him as much higher and greater Honour: and like men of deeper Reaſon, plead that equal Honour is due to Chriſt the Son and the Father, from that very Text that the <hi>Arians</hi> expreſly ſay was miſtaken to that purpoſe, as thoſe Fathers obſerve alſo.</p>
               <p>If we ſhould enquire what ſhould be the reaſon, why both the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> and <hi>Arians</hi> too, are ſo careful to diſtinguiſh of the Objects and Degrees of their Worſhip, what reaſon can offer it ſelf but this? namely, to ſecure themſelves from the charge and guilt of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> They all agreed in the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; that thoſe that give the ſame honour to any Creature that is due to God, is <hi>Idolatry.</hi> They all agreed in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that leaves our <hi>Socinian</hi> without excuſe.</p>
               <p>'Tis plain in the Holy Scriptures, God would preſerve his People from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> by that firſt and great Command, which is but a beam of the light of <hi>Nature; Thou ſhalt have</hi> (that is, thou ſhalt Worſhip) <hi>no other God but me,</hi> or before me; 'tis as if he had ſaid, this is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Adultery,</hi> my jealouſie will not endure it. The ſame great Argument wherewith our Saviour reſiſted, refuted, and repell'd the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> when he was Tempted by him to commit Idolatry. <hi>It is written, thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I call this great Principle, a <hi>Beam</hi> of the light of <hi>Nature,</hi> and the reaſon of Mankind, ſeeing not only <hi>Jews, Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> and <hi>Arians,</hi> but even <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> as well as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> are united in it, and concur together to condemn and aggravate the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Socinians.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106798:7"/>
               <p> The juſt Concluſion of the whole is this; that by the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Teſtimony of <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> and by the joint and unanimous conſent of all the <hi>World,</hi> beſides themſelves, the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> by allowing the ſame Worſhip to the Creature, that is proper and peculiar to the great God, are pronounced guilty of the moſt ſcandalous and fouleſt <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. Socinians <hi>allow Religious Worſhip without</hi> Diſtinction <hi>to a</hi> Creature.</head>
               <p>PErhaps it may be yet thought requiſite, to enquire a little farther into two things. 1. Whether the <hi>Socinians</hi> do indeed allow Divine and Religious Worſhip, as ſuch with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſtinction to a Creature. 2. If ſo? Why they do it? Theſe things well examined the Argument may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what clearer.</p>
               <p>1. To begin with the <hi>Firſt</hi> of them, That <hi>Socinus</hi> and his Adhearents and Party do allow ſuch Worſhip to a meer Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in their own Opinion, cannot be doubted by any that read their Books, and know their Opinion of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and the Honour and Worſhip they allow him, and argue for.</p>
               <p>I know there is a <hi>Party</hi> that go under the Name of <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that deny our Saviour ought ſo to be Worſhipped, for this very reaſon, becauſe he is a <hi>Creature;</hi> and joyn with us in charging the guilt of <hi>Idolatry</hi> upon thoſe that do ſo; theſe we may have ſomething to ſay to by and by; but as for <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and his Party, I would lay this Argument before them, and deſire their plain and honeſt anſwer to it. Thoſe that give Divine Honour to a Creature are Guilty of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> but <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> as well as <hi>Papiſt,</hi> give Divine Honour to a Creature, therefore they are both guilty of <hi>Idolatry.</hi> The <hi>Papiſt</hi> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only the ſecond Propoſition by diſtinguiſhing their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, allow the firſt; and indeed their Learned Men are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, that to give <hi>Latria</hi> to any Creature is <hi>Adolatry:</hi> And tho' they generally confound and neglect their diſtinctions in their Practices, yet that conſideration farther confirms their Conceſſion of the firſt Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That 'tis <hi>Idolatry</hi> to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106798:8"/> give Divine Worſhip or <hi>Latria</hi> to a Creature; ſeeing they chooſe rather to deny plain and manifeſt matter of fact, and bear any Contradiction betwixt their Doctrine and Practice, then dare to queſtion a Propoſition, that is Self-evident to all Mankind, as the firſt Propoſition in the Argument is.</p>
               <p>But, which Propoſition will our <hi>Socinian</hi> deny, ſure not the <hi>Minor;</hi> that they may not give Religious Worſhip to a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For they ſay, Chriſt is no more, and yet allow Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Worſhip to be given to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socinus</hi> himſelf ſpeaks home <hi>(Conſtanter aſſerimus &amp; quidem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Reſp. ad <hi>Bland.</hi> Tom. 2. p. 716.</note> 
                  <hi>jure) We conſtantly affirm, that we may of right direct our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Chriſt, and tho' he can find no command for it,</hi> yet he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>praying</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>becauſe of the Kingdom Power and Government given to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let their publick <hi>Catechiſm</hi> witneſs for them, they having granted Divine honour due to Chriſt, they ask wherein it conſiſts; and anſwer, in Worſhipping and Praying to him: and ſay, farther, 'tis our <hi>Duty</hi> to Worſhip him: and then that ſevere and damning ſentence againſt their Brethren that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it is pronounced. <hi>Seing Chriſtians,</hi> ſay they, <hi>are deſcribed as ſuch as call upon the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 'tis eaſy to underſtand, that thoſe that will not do it are no Chriſtians,</hi> Cat. Rac. <hi>ſ.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 88. 92. Thus, they freely and fairly grant the Two Propoſitions: but what do they ſay to the firſt, that Divine Worſhip paid to a Creature is <hi>Idolatry?</hi> Here they heſitate, and ſeem a little afraid to ſpeak out, leaſt they ſhould ſeem either to fight with a Beam of the Sun, or pronounce themſelves <hi>Idolaters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>Socinus</hi> himſelf ſeems to be at ſome loſs, and returns back to the ſecond Propoſition, and forbears to conſider Chriſt as a Creature, while he is the Object of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and to reſpect him ſo far a <hi>God,</hi> as to be fit to be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip'd. <hi>Cum neceſſe ſit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>eum cujus nomen in voces pro deo competente ſenſu colere,</hi> &amp;c. But will <hi>Socinus</hi> ſay, that this his God, whom he Worſhips with Divine Worſhip meaning Chriſt, is not a Creature ſtill? O yes, this ſtrikes at the Foundation, he is a Creature ſtill. How then comes it to paſs that 'tis no <hi>Idolatry</hi> to Worſhip him with Worſhip due only to God, that is no Creature. And how ſhall the firſt Propoſition ſtand good, that 'tis Idolatry to Worſhip any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106798:8"/> Creature with Divine Worſhip, to ſay he is Gods <hi>Deputy</hi> and Commiſſioner, and therefore Divine Worſhip is due to him, will as well excuſe the <hi>Pagan;</hi> and to ſay, he is <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> betwixt God and us, will equally excuſe the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as the <hi>Socinian</hi> Idolatry. But by the ſame reaſon that we allow the ſame kind of Worſhip that is due to the Supream God, to our Lord Jeſus, muſt we not acknowledge him to be the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream God too? <hi>Qui rogat ille facit:</hi> Therefore, by giving him the ſame Worſhip, do not we make him the ſame God, proportionably to the Worſhip we give him: The higheſt kind, to the Supream or Higheſt God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Volkelius,</hi> having raiſed his Admiration of our Saviour with the Conſideration of the many Excellencies and Honours God had given him, breaks out with theſe words; <hi>Quis, inquam, Hunc Divino Honore digniſſimum non exiſtimet, ideoque Sanctiſſimo Cultu non afficiat?</hi> Who would not count him worthy of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> Honour, and pay him the moſt Holy Worſhips? But would <hi>Volkelius</hi> ſay, he was not a <hi>Creature</hi> ſtill? That ſpoils his Rhetorick and Argument too.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that tho' Chriſt be but a Creature, yet if God Commands us to Worſhip him with the ſame Worſhip that is due to himſelf, 'tis then no <hi>Idolatry;</hi> 'tis our duty to do ſo. This is ſaid by ſome, but without Proof or Credit. It impoſeth upon the <hi>Almighty,</hi> as if he had done that, which he hath <hi>Sworn</hi> he will not do, <hi>viz. Give his glory to another.</hi> I ſee no way left for them to eſcape the charge of <hi>Idolary,</hi> but to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our <hi>Saviour</hi> to be more than a Creature, as we do; or to deny him the Honour due to <hi>God,</hi> as their <hi>Brethren</hi> of the other Perſwaſion do: for the reaſon and definition of <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> is Eternal and Immutable, and Inflexible, and will not bend to any of their new Notions or ſubtle Invaſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scachinglius</hi> upon the firſt to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſpeaks home; the Apoſtle, ſaith he, teacheth, That the Creator only, <hi>Excluſis omnibus Creaturis,</hi> is to be Religiouſly Worſhipped, and that it is a Sin either to <hi>neglect</hi> to Worſhip the Creator, or to joyn Religious Worſhip to the <hi>Creature,</hi> with the Worſhip of the <hi>Creator.</hi> Now, who could have ſaid any thing better? And yet who could defend his own great Opinion more abſurdly and weakly againſt this confeſſed Doctrine of the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle? All that he offers is this; That, notwithſtanding
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106798:9"/> God hath given this Worſhip and Honour to Chriſt, tho' a Creature: But where hath God alter'd the Nature of, or diſpenced with <hi>Idolatry?</hi> Where doth it appear, that God hath chang'd his Vow'd purpoſe, and given his Glory to a Creature? Doth not the plain Doctrine both of the Old and New Teſtament; and many examples both of Men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the very Natures of God and the Creature, and the ſence of all Mankind, reprove his Vanity, and forbid any Credit to be given to his empty evaſion that ſo evidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts the Apoſtles Text, and his own obſervation upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wolzog</hi> and <hi>Smalcius</hi> ſpeak out indeed, The <hi>Firſt</hi> is bold to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Matth.</hi> 4. 10. p. 189.</note> ſay, That Divine Worſhip, which is due to the moſt high God, is now due to Chriſt; and before, was to be given to <hi>Angels, Jure Meritoque,</hi> as their juſt deſert. And the <hi>Second</hi> as confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eraſ.</hi> 17. and 100.</note> aſſures us, that God may Command that any one of the Angels may be Worſhipped <hi>Pro Deo,</hi> for God. And he calls the Angels <hi>Dii Caeleſtes,</hi> to whom Divine Worſhip may be given, and was actually under the Law. The ground of this Confidence is only this, <hi>Quod omnis Legatus Suſtinet perſonam Mittentis,</hi> and the ſame Honour is due to him that is ſent, by Virtue of his very Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>Now, here our Divines ſubvert the ground of this Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; Firſt, by denying the matters of Fact, That the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> were Worſhipped with Divine Worſhip, much leſs by Gods own Permiſſion or Precept, in the time of the <hi>Law,</hi> which they boldly impoſe without proof.</p>
               <p>Again, we anſwer, if God cannot <hi>deny</hi> himſelf, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Command a Creature to be Worſhipped <hi>Pro Deo,</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and give his <hi>Glory to another;</hi> and he hath ſworn, if he can, he will not.</p>
               <p>Further, this Ancient right of <hi>Angels</hi> to be ſo Worſhipped, if it were proved, would ſerve indeed to extenuate the guilt of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Idolatry, who diſtinguiſh of their Worſhip, and deny in their Doctrine, what theſe ſo ſhameleſly aſſert, That the Worſhip due to God can be due to any Creature; but cannot reach the height of this <hi>Socinian</hi> Doctrine, that without <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction,</hi> Divine Worſhip, or as they ſpeak, the Worſhip due to the moſt <hi>High God,</hi> may <hi>Jure &amp; merito,</hi> be given to a Creature.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding their Reaſon, that they bear the <hi>Perſon</hi> of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106798:9"/> God himſelf as his <hi>Delegates</hi> and Commiſſioners. For this doth not make them really <hi>Gods, i. e.</hi> proper Objects of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Honour: Or if the Argument were good, it would go a great way farther, than they themſelves would have any colour to allow. For then, not only <hi>Angels,</hi> but the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and every <hi>Miniſter</hi> being <hi>ſent</hi> by God, as his Legates and Miſſioners, have Right to the ſame Worſhip that is due to God that ſends them, as well as Angels; this ſufficiently ſhames the Argument: Yet 'tis further obſerved, that tho' St. <hi>Peter</hi> was our Saviours <hi>Legate</hi> to <hi>Cornelius,</hi> yet he with ſome Zeal for his God, refuſed the <hi>Adoration;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Ariſe, for I my ſelf am a Man alſo,</hi> not ſuffering him to comply with the <hi>Socinian</hi> Doctrine, contrary to the ſtanding fence againſt Temptations to <hi>Idolatry</hi> uſed by our Saviour: 'tis writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Thou ſhalt Worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve,</hi> as we noted before; and cannot two often think upon, while we have to do with ſuch Adverſaries and Arguments.</p>
               <p>But that we may have full proof, that theſe men dare ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſay any thing to ſave their <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> They take cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ſay, That 'tis no <hi>Idolatry</hi> to give Divine Worſhip to a Creature, for this incomprehenſible reaſon: <hi>Non certum eſt,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Smalcius, Deum ob Naturam Divinam, praeciſe Colendum eſſe:</hi> i. e. 'Tis not certain that 'tis morally due to God, to be Worſhiped with a Worſhip worthy of God. 'Tis not of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> but by <hi>Poſitive</hi> Law, to give the Supream God, Supream Honour: This is ſuch a ſtretch of Reaſon or Confidence, as 'tis pity to anſwer or reflect upon. If there be any thing <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> in the <hi>Decaloque,</hi> certainly this is it, <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other God but me;</hi> namely, to give Divine Worſhip to. If there be any ſuch thing as <hi>Natural</hi> Religion, theſe are the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed branches of it, that there <hi>is a God,</hi> and that he ought to be <hi>Worſhipped,</hi> and as a God too, <hi>Purâ mente Colindus,</hi> if there be any duty reſulting from the <hi>Relation</hi> of a Creature to its Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, 'tis this, to give him the Service and Honour of its Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, when Men are driven to ſuch a paſs of invention and ſhift, they have abundantly expoſed their Cauſe themſelves, and 'tis time to leave them under this Conviction; that, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their ſubterfuges, ſeeing they allow the ſame Honour and Worſhip to the Creature (without <hi>Diſtinction)</hi> that is due to the chief God, as they expreſs it, they are guilty of <hi>Idolatry</hi> in a fouler and more ſcandalous manner than the <hi>Papiſt</hi> are. <hi>q. e. d.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106798:10"/>
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Why</hi> Socinus <hi>Adored Chriſt, his Arguments againſt</hi> David, <hi>for it prepared for.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus we are lead to the <hi>Second</hi> enquiry propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> Why the <hi>Socinians</hi> allow our Saviour, tho' a mere Creature in their Opinion, the ſame Honour and Worſhip which is due to the Supream God.</p>
               <p>This is an inquiry of conſiderable moment; for it muſt be acknowledged that <hi>Socinus</hi> and his Followers herein, are Men of admirable Reaſon; and unleſs it were for ſome importent end or purpoſe, they would not at once deny a Truth which every one elſe agree in; namely, That Religious Worſhip is due only to the Supream God; and yet affirm, that it may even in the <hi>ſame</hi> degree or kind be given to Chriſt, tho' a meer Creature. To ſay, they do this only to avoid the <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal</hi> of diſhonouring our Lord, and offending other Chriſtians, as <hi>Blandrat</hi> ſeems to intimate to <hi>Socinus;</hi> ſeems too weak an account of this weighty matter; ſeeing that might at leaſt, in part have been avoided, by diſtinguiſhing of Worſhip, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do; but they do not.</p>
               <p>The plain truth ſeems to be this; the Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> abound with Arguments for the Worſhipping of Chriſt as <hi>God;</hi> ſo glar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he could not outface them, tho' herein <hi>Socinus</hi> ſeems evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to deny his own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in reverence to <hi>Revelation,</hi> which is rare in him; and to deſtroy his own dear <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> as well as confute his Adverſary.</p>
               <p>For while he allows truely Religious Worſhip to be given to our <hi>Saviour,</hi> he thereby grants him to be more than a <hi>Creature;</hi> that is the Supream <hi>God,</hi> both in the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the thing, the natural <hi>Conſequence</hi> of his Conceſſion, and in the juſt ſentence of the other <hi>Socinian</hi> Party, I mean <hi>Fr. David</hi> and his Adherents.</p>
               <p>Here I crave leave to fix my foot, and with theſe other kind of <hi>Unitarians</hi> I do affirm, and am provided to maintain, if need be, that <hi>Socinus</hi> and his Followers, muſt either acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Saviour to be <hi>more</hi> then a Creature, and become an <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox</hi> Chriſtian in this point; or that they are <hi>Idolaters</hi> in a more Scandalous manner then the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> ſeeing they make
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106798:10"/> to themſelves a <hi>God</hi> of a <hi>Creature,</hi> by aſcribing the Worſhip due to the Supream to their <hi>Creature-God;</hi> and ſeeing they profeſſedly Worſhip <hi>Two</hi> Gods, let them no longer glory in the Name of <hi>Unitarians,</hi> but leave it for <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> who better deſerve it.</p>
               <p>But I muſt beg leave to digreſs a little on <hi>Socinus</hi>'s part, who hath as effectually baffled <hi>Francis David</hi> by clear Scripture Proof, that our Saviour is to be Religiouſly Worſhip'd; as the ſaid <hi>David</hi> was too hard for <hi>Socinus</hi> in the other point; that our Saviour being ſuppoſed to be a meer Creature, it is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry ſo to Worſhip him, and if he ought ſo to be Worſhipped, he is more then a Creature, <hi>i. e.</hi> Truly a <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I find this Argument hath put ſome to ſecond thoughts; they begin to ſtartle and are afraid of <hi>Idolatry:</hi> And therefore ſay, that ſome <hi>Unitarians</hi> are contrary minded; and believe our Saviour ought not to be Religiouſly Worſhipped and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as <hi>God:</hi> And this is the ſide, to which they ſeem now to lean, for fear of <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis for the ſake of theſe chiefly, that I deſire to dilate a little about this great Article, and I earneſtly beſeech them ſeriouſly to weigh a few things before they determine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> You change ſides for the worſe: You leave your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Socinus,</hi> who was certainly more like a Chriſtian, and cleave to <hi>David</hi> and his party, that are more open and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Enemies of our Lord and Saviour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> You lean to a Party that brandeth the firſt and great founder of <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> with groſs <hi>Idolatry;</hi> and to avoid <hi>Idolatry,</hi> by giving Chriſt more than you think is due; you come within the peril of <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and rob him of that which is of right due to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider, if it do appear that Chriſt ought to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Adored and Worſhipped; the Conſequence is irreſiſtible in <hi>Francis Davids</hi> Judgment, as well as in the thing it ſelf: <hi>We cannot,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Adore the Son, unleſs we ſuppoſe Chriſt to be in the Father, and the Father in Chriſt,</hi> Unitate Eſſentiae, <hi>by unity of Eſſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly and Laſtly,</hi> Seriouſly conſider the Arguments of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinus</hi> himſelf (and we need no other) before you leave him, in ſo great a point, wherein he is certainly in the right; that Chriſt ought to be Religiouſly Adored and Worſhipped, what ever the conſequence may be.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106798:11"/>
               <p> Seeing you incline to believe that <hi>David</hi>'s point is well fixed; and that Religiouſly to Adore and Worſhip any Creature is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as we have all along maintained: If <hi>Socinus</hi> make good his point too, That Chriſt is to be Religiouſly Adored and Worſhipped, let the <hi>Orthodox</hi> truth find its way by theſe lights; and preſerve or recover its place, in our <hi>Faith</hi> as good Chriſtians, touching our Saviours Divinity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. Socinus <hi>and his Parties Arguments, that Chriſt is to be</hi> Religiouſly Worſhipped.</head>
               <p>LET us now take a brief Survey of <hi>Socinus</hi> and his parties Arguments to prove, that we may and ought to give Religious Adoration and Worſhip to our Saviour. They do it ſufficiently under theſe Three Heads. <hi>Profit, Neceſſity,</hi> and <hi>Example.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis our <hi>Intereſt</hi> and conſequently our Wiſdom thus to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Profit.</hi>
                  </note> Worſhip him. The <hi>Rac. Catechiſ.</hi> teacheth, That <hi>We ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that Chriſt is able to do all things;</hi> and that, <hi>if we ſeek his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">S. 6. C. 1. L. 88. 89.</note> 
                  <hi>favour, he will do us good, and perform all his promiſes to us;</hi> and infer, thence, that <hi>We ought to truſt in Chriſt in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as we ought to truſt in God.</hi> Again, they ſay, <hi>We may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our Prayers to him in all our neceſſities, becauſe he both can and will help us, and he underſtands our Prayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis our neceſſary <hi>Duty</hi> both with reſpect to his <hi>Perſon,</hi> and <note place="margin">2. <hi>Neceſſity.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Law</hi> of his Father: <hi>Socinus</hi> himſelf infers a neceſſity of Praying to Chriſt, becauſe of the <hi>Kingdom, Power</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given to him,</hi> as before we obſerved: And in the Law of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Blands</hi> Tom. 2. p. 716, 721.</note> the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to pray to Chriſt, is made the very <hi>Condition</hi> of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. <hi>Socinus</hi> acknowledgeth (againſt <hi>Fr. David)</hi> that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the Prophet, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 32. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall call on the Name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved,</hi> is juſtly applied to Chriſt, by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 13. Yea, this is the very Character the Holy Scriptures give us of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> he is one that <hi>calls on the Name of Chriſt, Act.</hi> 14. 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 22. and their own <hi>Catechiſm</hi> aſſerts peremptorily, as we noted before, that they are no <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that <hi>will not</hi> pray to Chriſt; who tell us plainly and expreſly, that 'tis our <hi>Duty to Worſhip him,</hi> and prove it from, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 22, 23. <hi>All ſhould honour the Son as they honour the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106798:11"/> 3. Their <hi>Catechiſm</hi> aſſures us, that we may pray unto Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Examples.</hi> p. 89.</note> we have ſeveral Inſtances of Holy Men, who have done ſo. His own <hi>Diſciples</hi> prayed unto him, when he was upon the <hi>Earth</hi> for <hi>Temporal</hi> deliverance: <hi>Lord ſave us we periſh,</hi> Matth. 8. 25. And even for <hi>Spiritual</hi> Grace: <hi>Lord increaſe our Faith.</hi> And after he was gone to <hi>Heaven,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> the great Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed ſo effectually againſt <hi>Pagan Idolatry,</hi> pray'd unto him more then once, <hi>I,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>beſought the Lord thrice,</hi> and his Lord aſſured him, he did well in ſo doing, in this gracious anſwer, <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 7, 8, 9. So far <hi>Socinus</hi> himſelf; his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers further obſerve, that the ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> joyns Chriſt with God the <hi>Father,</hi> in his prayer mentioned to the <hi>Theſſalonians, Now God himſelf and our Father and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, direct our way unto you;</hi> and at other times, does the ſame in effect, in his <hi>Salutations</hi> to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Churches when he wiſheth them, <hi>Grace, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> equally from God the Father and the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Theſe inſtances, I hope are ſufficient, I ſhall add one more, and that is a very plain one; and one would imagine beyond exception: 'Tis St. <hi>Stephen</hi> praying in theſe words, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit,</hi> Act. 7. 59. but behold the fineneſs of <hi>Fr. Davids</hi> Invention; ſaith he, 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> may be either the <hi>Genetive</hi> or the <hi>Vocative</hi> Caſe, according to the uſual art of <hi>Socinian</hi> reaſoning, it muſt be taken in that ſence, that will beſt ſerve a <hi>Turn,</hi> tho' never ſo alien or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true interpretation, and the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the Context, he muſt have it, <hi>Lord of Jeſus,</hi> or elſe it will prove either that 'tis Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Worſhip our Saviour, and to pray unto him; or this firſt <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> died with <hi>Idolatry</hi> in his mouth.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Criticiſm</hi> is not ſo fine, as 'tis forced and abſurd. The Learned obſerve, that if <hi>[Jeſus]</hi> had been the <hi>Genitive Caſe,</hi> the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> would have been added; 'twould have been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. We find the ſame words <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 20. and there they cannot bear the ſence of the <hi>Genitive,</hi> and muſt be underſtood in the <hi>Vocative Caſe:</hi> But, beſides the ilneſs of the <hi>Grammer,</hi> the harſhneſs of the <hi>Sence,</hi> and the <hi>Novelty</hi> of this rare diſcovery; two or three things might abate the Authors confident boaſting of this Invention: The <hi>Syriac</hi> is beyond the reach, of it, <hi>Domine Noſter Jeſu.</hi> Some Copies have it plainer yet, and Read it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, O Lord Chriſt. And their admired <hi>Grotius</hi>'s gloſs is utterly inconſiſtent with it, <hi>Invocantem nempe Jeſum Chriſtum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> But why ſhould I trouble my <hi>Reader</hi> any farther about this Ridiculous ſhift of <hi>David,</hi> which you may find was long ſince ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and baffled by <hi>Socinus</hi> himſelf in a very ſtrenuous confutation of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106798:12"/> it, which its Author <hi>David</hi> had never courage or skill enough, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter again, that I can find.</p>
               <p>Now my Brethren conſider, 'tis eternal <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that Reliouſly to Worſhip any Creature is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> but we have found it the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practice of the beſt men in <hi>Scripture,</hi> thus Religiouſly to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip our Saviour Chriſt it ſeems to follow clearly, that either theſe Holy Men ſo doing, were <hi>Idolaters,</hi> or our Saviour Chriſt is more then a meer <hi>Creature,</hi> that is, he is the <hi>True God.</hi> I know you will deny the <hi>Firſt:</hi> I heartily wiſh you would confeſs the <hi>Second,</hi> it would be ſo far well betwixt us.</p>
               <p>However, you do not undertake to defend the part of <hi>Socinus</hi> from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> more haynous then that of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> which I hope I have demonſtrated ſufficiently before.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The</hi> Socinians Antiſcripturiſt, <hi>as truly as, if not more then the</hi> Papiſts.</head>
            <p>HAving ended our <hi>Firſt Parrable,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Socinian</hi> and <hi>Papiſt,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>Term</hi> of Worſhip, we come next to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with reſpect to their <hi>Rule</hi> of Faith, the <hi>Canonical</hi> Books of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Herein alſo they both concur, <hi>viz.</hi> In their endeavours to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine their Authority: And when they think they have occaſion ſo to do, they lay this <hi>Rule</hi> aſide, and ſet up <hi>another</hi> of their own, in the ſtead of it.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do ſo the <hi>Socinians</hi> readily grant; and that the <hi>Socians</hi> do like the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and exceed them therein, is as eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>The</hi> Papiſts <hi>vilifies the Holy</hi> Scripture.</head>
               <p>1. FOR the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the World is ſenſible enough, how vilely they deal with this <hi>Rule</hi> of the Holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and make them indeed, as they ſometimes call them, <hi>A Noſe of Wax,</hi> and a <hi>Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Rule:</hi> They take upon them to <hi>ſence</hi> them as they pleaſe; and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106798:12"/> uſe them only as <hi>Tools</hi> to ſerve a turn, and little otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>Sometimes, they will admit nothing but the bare <hi>Words,</hi> without any reaſonable Conſtruction of them; when they would advance their <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> At other times, when the proper and <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Sence</hi> is againſt them, O then the Scripture is a <hi>Killing,</hi> a <hi>Dead</hi> Letter, and muſt receive its <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Senſe</hi> from their <hi>Churches</hi> Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, how wild and abſurd ſoever it be to ſerve their <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, when they have diſparaged, ſleighted, and ſet aſide the <hi>True Rule,</hi> 'tis no wonder they introduce and obtrude <hi>another Rule</hi> of their own deviſing, which they do not only make equal with it, but prefer before it; I mean their Oral <hi>Tradition,</hi> and the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: Yea, when they ſeem to allow the Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> any Authority, they at the ſame time rob them of it, by transfering that Authority to themſelves, their own Sence and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents, tho' diverſe from, and even contrary to the Letter, or plain and obvious meaning of the <hi>Written</hi> Word.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>The</hi> Socinians <hi>vilifie the</hi> Scripture <hi>more then</hi> Papiſts.</head>
               <p>WHile I have been ſpeaking of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> I have given you but an imperfect draught and <hi>Character</hi> of a <hi>Socinian</hi> in this point: Verily, the <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſeems to be the honeſter of the two: His is an open and down-right attacking and villifying thoſe Holy Books; while the <hi>Socinian</hi> doth it in diſguiſe, and wounds it deeper; lies in its <hi>Boſom,</hi> and ſtabbs it to the <hi>Heart;</hi> and with ſplended Colours of Honouring, and Arguments proving its Divine <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> makes it utter <hi>Non-ſenſe,</hi> bad <hi>ſenſe,</hi> or any ſence, that their cauſe requires.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing theſe men, in other things, are Maſters of a great deal of Reaſon; it may be worth a Queſtion, whether their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo much for the Divine Authority of the Holy Scriptures, be from a real Opinion of the Truth of it, or only in <hi>pretence,</hi> to ſerve their own purpoſe, and varniſh their deſigns: For, how is it poſſible, if their Opinion of it were <hi>Real,</hi> they ſhould uſe it ſo ſlightly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo trifling a manner, as 'tis pitty, to ſee they do.</p>
               <p>With how much gravity and ſolemn circumſtances, do they make the Word of God <hi>Felo de ſe;</hi> not ſo much by <hi>oppoſing,</hi> as by <hi>Appoſing</hi> one part to another; and by the idleſt <hi>Phanſies,</hi> or an odd kind of skill peculiar to themſelves, make a <hi>weaker</hi> text, take off the life and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106798:13"/> ſenſe of a <hi>Stronger,</hi> and by a <hi>likeneſs,</hi> or ſameneſs, or neerneſs of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion (when there is no other reaſon in the World for it) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ervate the ſtrength of the beſt Arguments it affords, for the <hi>God-head</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>Sacred Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make this out beyond exception, give me leave only to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome Inſtances of it: The mention only, is ſhame and reproach enough, one would think, as well as confutation, in the ſenſe of an <hi>Indifferent</hi> or modeſt Man.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When we prove <hi>Three Perſons</hi> and each of them <hi>God,</hi> from the great <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for <hi>Propagating</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, by <hi>Baptiſing in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> They gravely anſwer, and would have us take it for a full Anſwer; That 'tis ſaid, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were Baptized into <hi>Moſes and in the Cloud;</hi> and that <hi>they believed in God, and his Servant</hi> Moſes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we urge, <hi>John</hi> 1. 1. <hi>In the beginning was the Word;</hi> they reply that it muſt ſignifie, the <hi>Beginning</hi> of the Goſpel or <hi>New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> And their proof is, becauſe we read <hi>[from the Beginning]</hi> in that latter ſence, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 2. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 1. 1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When to prove our Saviour's <hi>Incarnation,</hi> we uſe the Apoſtles words, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>The Word was made Fleſh;</hi> they ſay, we muſt not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by <hi>Fleſh</hi> there, the Humane <hi>Nature,</hi> but a State of Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; becauſe in that ſence, the word <hi>[Fleſh]</hi> is ſomewhere elſe to be underſtood.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Where our Saviour tells us, <hi>John</hi> 18. 28. <hi>That he and his Father are one;</hi> They ſay, that is, they are one only in <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, becauſe our Saviour Prays, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. that his Diſciples <hi>may be one, as he and his Father are one; i. e.</hi> Not in <hi>Nature,</hi> but in mind and heart: and this muſt be all the meaning of our Saviour in the place we have mentioned, notwithſtanding the obvious evidence of the Text to the contrary, <hi>viz.</hi> That he and his Father are one, in <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and conſequently in <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is not only the general Sence of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> that weighs little with <hi>Socinians;</hi> but alſo of their admired <hi>Grotius</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> whom they claim for their own. <hi>Si pereant meâ infirmitate. Patris poteſtas mea poteſtas;</hi> my Fathers Power, is my Power, <hi>Grot.</hi> in <hi>Loc. Potentior eſt ad ſervandum,</hi> Eraſ. <hi>in</hi> Loc.</p>
               <p n="5">5. So our Lord Chriſt muſt be a God by <hi>Office</hi> only, and not by Nature, Why? Becauſe they find <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> are called <hi>Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. When we read <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 16. That by Chriſt <hi>were Created all things that are in Heaven and that are in Earth, whether viſible and inviſible; whether they be Thornes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>all things were created by him and for him:</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106798:13"/> They reſtrain all this to the <hi>Second</hi> Creation or Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and thoſe great words ſignifies onely <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> of Men on <hi>Earth:</hi> Confounding Heaven and Earth, viſible and inviſible, denying any thing that looks againſt them; and not ſticking to ſay any thing that their <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> ſeems to need.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Name <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> with ſo much ſolemnity given by an <hi>Angel</hi> from Heaven to Chriſt, doth not ſignifie the <hi>Union</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane Nature in him; becauſe others might have been called ſo before, as ſince ſome have; as <hi>Eniedine</hi> gravely inſtanceth in <hi>Emmanuel Tremelius.</hi> Theſe things are childiſh and Rediculous, and deſerve a ſevere Reflection, not any ſerious confutation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. Socinian <hi>Chriticiſms in Articles.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus the <hi>Socinians</hi> bandy the Scriptures one againſt another; and 'tis hard to think that they believe themſelves to be in earneſt, while they are found <hi>Ludere cara ſacris,</hi> and impoſe ſuch childrens play, tho' never ſo ſolemnly upon the World; eſpecially, if we conſider their School-boys <hi>Criticiſms;</hi> and that, with a little <hi>Point,</hi> or a ſmall <hi>Article,</hi> they would weaken and deſtroy the Arguments of the greateſt and ſtrongeſt Texts in the Word of God againſt them; wherein, indeed the <hi>Arians</hi> lead them the way.</p>
               <p>They are both of them confident, that when <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſignifies the <hi>Father,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Articles.</hi>
                  </note> or the Supream God, in Scripture, it hath its <hi>Article</hi> always before it; but when the <hi>Son</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 'tis without an Article prefix'd to it. A mighty fine obſervation, this ſufficient doubtleſs, to evacuate one of the cleareſt and ſtrongeſt Arguments for our Lords <hi>Divinity,</hi> to diſtinguiſh the Natures of the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son;</hi> and to put a final end to this great Controverſie, tho' it hath no foundation in <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Grammer,</hi> much leſs in the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> as confident as they are.</p>
               <p>Indeed, they truly obſerve, that by [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] in <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 15. ſignified <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Article</hi> is prefixed; But doth it follow, that 'tis always ſo? within the compaſs of two or three ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes afterwards, they may ſee their Obſervation utterly undone, <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>ver.</hi> 6. for there the Father is call'd God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without an Article. So likewiſe in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 1. the Son is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle: And if <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without an Article is found to ſignifie God the <hi>Father,</hi> Why may it not ſignifie the God-head of the <hi>Son</hi> likewiſe, tho' it have not an Article before it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 5. would help them to avoid the force of that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106798:14"/> great Text, for the proof of our Lords <hi>Divinity,</hi> with a <hi>Point,</hi> which looks like <hi>Puſh-pin</hi> Divinity indeed: <hi>Punctum poſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>vel poſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, chooſe you whether. But <hi>Eraſmus</hi> himſelf confeſſeth, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe <hi>Nicities</hi> in <hi>Pointing,</hi> all the <hi>Greek</hi> Copies have it as we read it; and refers the Relative <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Chriſt, which is plainly more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, as the Learn'd obſerve, both to the <hi>Scope</hi> of the Apoſtle, and the <hi>Series</hi> of the words.</p>
               <p>Beſides, 'Tis worthy our obſervation, that tho' <hi>Eraſmus</hi> is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to own, that Chriſt is here meant, but thinks <hi>God</hi> here, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, and is to be taken, <hi>vel pro totâ Triade, vel perſona Patris,</hi> yet by the ſame Words, he confeſſeth the <hi>Trinity;</hi> and conſequently the <hi>Deity</hi> of the Son, as he doth afterwards more expreſly, on thoſe two famous Texts, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 6. where theſe are his words upon the firſt of them, q. d. <hi>Qui cum eſſet &amp; ſit, non uſurpativus, ſed verus Deus, non eſtimavit aequalitatem Dei ſibi eſſe rapinam:</hi> and on the Second, <hi>Et etate praecedit, quia aeternus, &amp; dignitate, quia Naturalis,</hi> The Eternal and Natural Son of God, which is enough to vindicate <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> from being either <hi>Arian</hi> or <hi>Socinian:</hi> How ever ſome boaſt to the contrary; we hereby ſee what credit is to be given them.</p>
               <p>'Tis confeſſed, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> notes, that St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Hillary</hi> omit the word <hi>[Deus]</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 6. Yet 'tis concluded by the Learned, that it was omitted, not induſtriouſly by thoſe eminent <hi>Fathers,</hi> but <hi>in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Librariorum &amp; res ipſa oſtendit;</hi> 'tis evident it muſt be ſo, Seeing, both theſe <hi>Fathers</hi> cite this very <hi>Place,</hi> as a plain proof, that Chriſt is truly and properly God. <hi>Vid. Pol. Synop.</hi> in <hi>Loc.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>The</hi> Socinians <hi>Enervate the Authority of</hi> Gods Word.</head>
               <p>THey farther try their skill to looſen and weaken the Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> by <hi>Enervating</hi> the Credit of the Goſpel it ſelf, and making the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> if not the Lord Jeſus too, <hi>impertinent Sophiſters;</hi> while they Interpret the proofs, the inſpired Writing bring out of the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament, to confirm the New, into meer <hi>Alluſions</hi> and accomodations of Old Phraiſes or Expreſſions, without any further force and uſe of them. But this lays the Ax at the Root, and is of ſuch import and conſequence, that it deſerves a larger conſideration and reproof, then my preſent deſign will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106798:14"/>
               <head>SECT. V. Socinians <hi>have another Rule of their own, which they prefer above the Scripture.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have ſeen how perverſly and vilely, the <hi>Socinians</hi> treat the only <hi>Rule</hi> of the Chriſtian Faith; which yet, will appear more egregiouſly by our <hi>Second</hi> Obſervation; that they lay it aſide altogether, as a <hi>Rule;</hi> or meaſure it by a <hi>Rule</hi> of their own, which they ſet up in the room of it, or above, as the <hi>Papiſt</hi> do.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Socinian</hi> Rule, which they meaſure the Holy <hi>Scriptures, viz.</hi> The Divine <hi>Rule</hi> by, is nothing elſe, but their own private <hi>Senſe</hi> (if not their <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Phanſie)</hi> much the ſame with the <hi>Quakers</hi> Light within, which they call, <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have elſewhere diſtinguiſh'd, betwixt a <hi>Rule</hi> and a Judge; and obſerv'd, that <hi>theſe</hi> are not the ſame, but two diſtinct things, with reſpect to <hi>Religion:</hi> I ſhall explain and apply them more fully in the preſent Argument.</p>
               <p>We muſt in order hereunto diſtinguiſh, betwixt <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Explain't</hi>
                  </note> Religion, as ſuch.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I grant, with reſpect to meer <hi>Natural</hi> Religion, Reaſon ſeems to be both a <hi>Rule</hi> and a <hi>Judg,</hi> for we have nothing without our ſelves, that can well be conceived, to be either we know nothing of it, but the rational Notices, which Humane underſtanding ſuggeſt; or the Dictates of pure <hi>Reaſon</hi> called forth, or occaſioned by the works of <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Providence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But <hi>Revelation,</hi> being, from without us, is therefore a <hi>Rule</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on us from without; and muſt be diſtinct from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which is within us and part of our ſelves? and conſequently, tho' Reaſon be a Judge, it muſt Judge of <hi>Revealed</hi> Religion, by a <hi>Rule</hi> from <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> us; which is another thing, and not our <hi>Reaſon:</hi> I mean, we muſt Judge of Revealed Religion as ſuch, by that Rule by which that Religion is only made known to us, that is the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> and then, 'tis no wonder, if all our Religion as <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or Revealed, be not dictated or to be comprehended by Natural <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For if <hi>Reaſon</hi> had diſcovered all before, What need of <hi>Revelation?</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, thoſe that ſay, all our Religion, lies within the compaſs of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> are in a fair way to reject all <hi>Revelation;</hi> and to advance the <hi>Natural</hi> or <hi>Pagan</hi> Religion in the World, in the room of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:106798:15"/>
               <p> But ſeeing <hi>Socinus</hi> (tho' erroneouſly) ſuppoſeth, the <hi>Being</hi> of a God, could not have been diſcovered without <hi>Tradition</hi> or <hi>Revelation,</hi> how abſurd doth it ſeem (for him eſpecially) to imagine, that things that can be known only by <hi>Revelation,</hi> can be known or may be meaſured by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or any other Rule, but Revelation, or the Writing in and by which they are made known to Reaſon it ſelf, as <hi>Sencible</hi> Objects, being to be known only ſo far as <hi>Sence</hi> repreſents them to our imagination, can have no other <hi>Rule</hi> by which our <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> can Judge or meaſure them but our Sences.</p>
               <p>And, ſeeing our <hi>Revelation</hi> is from Heaven, we muſt not only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>Being</hi> of ſuch a Rule, but the <hi>Fulneſs,</hi> Rectitude, and <hi>Authority</hi> of it; by which, all the rules of <hi>Reaſon</hi> are to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, even in ſuch things as reaſon falls ſhort of, and could not have been any other way diſcovered; or being diſcovered, cannot be apprehended, but as they are Reveiled: if this be not granted, where is the Authority or Divinity of that <hi>Higher Rule,</hi> which is given by God, to be the only Rule and Standard of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion as ſuch?</p>
               <p>It hence follows, that this Divine <hi>Rule</hi> being ſuppoſed, Reaſon my Judge of it, but by no means, preſume to Judge it, ſo as to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, mind, alter, correct, or lay it aſide, or advance it ſelf above it.</p>
               <p>We muſt indeed, judge by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> what the things are that are ſo reveiled; we muſt meaſure all <hi>Articles</hi> impoſed on us, by our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon indeed; yet the <hi>Rule</hi> by which we are to do ſo, is only the Word of God: To exalt Reaſon or the inward rules or dictates of it, to be the meaſure of things reveil'd, is to lay aſide the <hi>True Rule,</hi> or to judge <hi>God</hi> himſelf in the Authority of his holy word.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Humane</hi> Judge, hath likewiſe his <hi>Rule</hi> without him, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Publick Laws:</hi> and if he ſhould make his private Sentiments of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Right, the rule of his Judgment, he falls under his Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors and every Mans Cenſure: 'Tis not his Office, to queſtion, or mend, or any way alter, much leſs abrogate the Law; but he is only <hi>Jus dicere,</hi> to declare and apply the Laws in his Jurisdiction; not to judge the <hi>Laws</hi> by the Rule of his own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but to uſe his Reaſon, to know and underſtand, and to paſs Judgment according to the Laws: much leſs, are we to queſtion the reaſonableneſs or equity of Gods Laws; or judge them unreaſonable or <hi>unfit</hi> for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures to give credit to; becauſe they ſeem not to ſquare with our Natural reaſon: This were to believe <hi>our ſelves</hi> and not God, to exalt our ſelves above God, yea to diſcredit and make God <hi>a Lyar.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106798:15"/>
               <p> I am ſorry we have ſo much reaſon to apply all this to <hi>Socinus</hi> and <note place="margin">Application</note> his Followers: how ſhall we forbear to arraign Arrogance, with the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> words, <hi>Thou art not a doer of the Law but a Judge. Who art thou,</hi> O vain Man, <hi>that replieſt againſt God.</hi> Is it not a marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous thing to ſee poor ignorant lapſed Man to errect a Tribunal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Maker; and with a ſhadow of Carnal Reaſon to ſit in Judgment upon <hi>Gods Word?</hi> and to level the greateſt <hi>Articles</hi> of the Chriſtian <hi>Faith,</hi> to their own ſhallow and partial apprehenſions? And yet thus the <hi>Socinian</hi> aſpires with his preſumptuous Reaſon, to dogmatize upon Revelation: To judge the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and all his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: His <hi>Generation, Incarnation, Natures, Offices, Paſſion, Satisfaction, Mediation</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion:</hi> To Judge and Condemn the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the ever <hi>Bleſſed Trinity;</hi> and to meaſure the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of our Bodies by the Model of his private apprehenſion.</p>
               <p>Yet this ſort of Men, ſhew great Reverence to, and very ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argue the Divine Authority of the Holy <hi>Scriptures:</hi> And they do not deny, but theſe great <hi>Articles</hi> are matters of pure <hi>Revelation</hi> in the ſame Scriptures: Neither can they evince any one of theſe great and miſterious Points, are repugnant to <hi>Sence</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or any other part of <hi>Gods Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Men ſhould have methinks, ſo much modeſty as to judge, that their corrupt <hi>Reaſon</hi> is as fallible as the <hi>Holy Pen-Men:</hi> Or, That it may be reaſonable we ſhould have a Rule <hi>without,</hi> to Diſcipline and bound our extravagant <hi>Phanſies</hi> in matters of <hi>Faith:</hi> Or that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reaſon, may be miſtaken in judging that a <hi>Contradiction,</hi> which the <hi>Church of God,</hi> I mean the generallity of <hi>Chriſtians, Semper &amp; ubique</hi> could never diſcover, and have hitherto verily believed, that it is none.</p>
               <p>I think 'tis plain, from what hath been ſaid, that the <hi>Socinian</hi> falls in with the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and goes beyond him, not only in villifying and laying aſide the True Rule of <hi>Faith,</hi> but in ſetting up another <hi>Rule</hi> of his own inſtead of it: They both are guilty, only with this difference: The <hi>Papiſt's</hi> Rule, is the <hi>Publick Reaſon</hi> and ſence of his Church; The <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians Rule</hi> is his own, and every particular Mans private <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and which of theſe is the wiſer and ſafer, let every Mans Reaſon judge.</p>
               <p>That I do not herein wrong the <hi>Socinian,</hi> almoſt all their Books have ſomething in them to bear me Witneſs. Let <hi>Smalcius</hi> more then once be heard for the reſt, Firſt, in that famous place of his.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Credimus inquit, etiam ſi non ſemel atque iterum, ſed ſatis crebro, &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tom. 1. Diſp. 6. Sect. 63.</note> 
                  <hi>Apartiſſime, Scriptum extaret, Deum eſſe hominem factum, multo ſatius eſſe, quia haec res ſit abſurda &amp; ſanae Rationi plane contraria, &amp; in Deum</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:106798:16"/> 
                  <hi>blaſphema, modum aliquem dicendi comminiſſi, quo iſta de Deo dici, quam iſta ſimpliciter ita ut verba ſonant, intelligere.</hi> i. e. Tho' we find it declared in Scripture, not only <hi>once</hi> and <hi>again,</hi> but <hi>very often,</hi> and very <hi>plainly,</hi> That <hi>God was made Man;</hi> becauſe this is abſurd, and plainly contrary to found <hi>Reaſon</hi> and Blaſphemous againſt God; <hi>We believe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that it is much better to find out ſome mode of ſpeaking, according to which one may ſay this concerning</hi> God, <hi>then to interpret things ſimply and according to the Letter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, let us hear him to the ſame purpoſe, if not more <note place="margin">Smal. Hom. 8. <hi>in</hi> c. 1. Joh. p. 89.</note> plainly in another place. <hi>Nullam Eſſe Religionis particulam quae cum ratione non Conveniat: Et quae cum Ratione non Convenit opinio, eam etiam in Theologiâ nullum locum habere poſſe:</hi> That is, that there is no ſmall point in Religion which doth not agree with Reaſon: And whatſoever Opinion doth not agree with <hi>Reaſon,</hi> can have no place even in <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What can this ſignifie? But that when an <hi>Article</hi> of Faith is plainly revealed in the Word of God, if it ſquare not with <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Reaſon, we muſt reject the evidence of Gods Authority, and hearken to <hi>Reaſon:</hi> That is in plain Engliſh, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and not the <hi>Scripture,</hi> is both the <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Rule of Socinian Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt conclude with an excellent paſſage or two, in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>Book</hi> of our Great <hi>Primate</hi> lately Printed, called his <hi>Sermons concerning the Divinity,</hi> &amp;c. of our Saviour. <q>I do readily grant, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> pag. 79. that the <hi>Socinian</hi> Writers have managed the Cauſe of the <hi>Reformation</hi> againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> with great acuteneſs and advantage in many reſpects: But I am ſorry to have cauſe to ſay, that they have likewiſe put into their hands, better and ſharper Weapons then ever they had before, for the weakning and undermining of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> which <hi>Socinus</hi> indeed hath in the general ſtrongly aſſerted; had he not by a dangerous liberty of impoſing a Forreign and forced Sence upon particular Texts, brought the whole into uncertainty.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Again <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> to ſpeak freely, I muſt needs ſay, that it ſeems to me a much fairer way to reject the Divine Authority of <note place="margin">p. 78. 79.</note> a <hi>Book,</hi> then to uſe it ſo diſingenuouſly, and to wreſt the plain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of it, with ſo much ſtraining and violence from their moſt Natural and Obvious ſence: For no Doctrine whatſoever can have any certain Foundation in any Book, if this liberty be once admitted, without regard to the plain Scope and Occaſion of it, to play upon the Words and Phraſes with all the Arts of <hi>Criticiſm,</hi> and with all the variety of <hi>Allegory</hi> which a brisk and lively ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination can deviſe.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106798:16"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Foundation of</hi> Socinianiſm, Fanatical <hi>as well as of the</hi> Papacy.</head>
            <p>WE have ſeen the <hi>Parallel,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>Term</hi> of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the <hi>Rule</hi> of Faith: We are now come to conſider how the <hi>Socinian</hi> and the <hi>Papiſt</hi> agree in the <hi>Foundation of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know, the pretenders to ſo much <hi>Reaſon,</hi> who make <hi>Reaſon</hi> to be both the <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> of their Religion, will ill bear the Title of <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſts;</hi> but 'tis poſſible, that even ſuch may be found, <hi>vel, cum, vel, ſine, Ratione Inſanire.</hi> If the <hi>Socinian</hi> appear to do ſo, he muſt not take it ill, to be rank'd with the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt</hi> in this charge alſo, and equally accuſed of <hi>Unreaſonable Religion,</hi> no better than <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> as well as <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripturiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this charge may appear fare and juſt; I ſhall firſt deſcribe what I mean by <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> or <hi>Enthuſiaſtical Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm,</hi> and then, I ſhall apply it to our preſent Subjects, the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Socinian,</hi> and ſee their agreement in it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. Fanaticiſm <hi>Deſcribed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOdern Fanaticiſm</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> I reckon to be nothing elſe, but a Religion (if it deſerve the Name) that hath no <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> either in the <hi>Word</hi> of God or ſound <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but is founded in <hi>Dreams</hi> or <hi>Phanſies,</hi> or pretended <hi>Inſpiration,</hi> or Divine <hi>Revelation</hi> beſides, and other then the <hi>Holy Scriptures:</hi> Now, whether I err in this <hi>Idea</hi> or Character of <hi>Fanaticiſm</hi> or no, yet I am ſure, that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that may be thus deſcribed, is a <hi>Wild</hi> or a <hi>Mad</hi> ſort of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>Socinians</hi> themſelves being <hi>Judges:</hi> Such is the Religion found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and is Fanatical and <hi>Enthuſiaſtical</hi> plain enough, as all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> acknowledge: And whether the <hi>Papacy</hi> as ſuch is much better, is doubted by all Learned <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> and how far <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm</hi> is liable to the ſame Condemnation, is to be enquired pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106798:17"/>
               <head>SECT. II. Fanaticiſm <hi>the Foundation of</hi> Popery.</head>
               <p>BUT, Firſt, for the <hi>Papacy,</hi> as ſuch that this hath no Foundation in <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon;</hi> That 'tis founded only in <hi>Dreams</hi> and <hi>Phanſies,</hi> and pretended <hi>Inſpiration</hi> or <hi>Revelation,</hi> will be eaſily grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if we conſider how their ſeveral <hi>Orders</hi> were firſt founded, namely in Fanatical <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> as is moſt evidently demonſtrated, by the excellent paines of a moſt <hi>Learned Prelate</hi> of our own now living. <note place="margin">Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
                  </note> Moreover, the very <hi>root</hi> of the <hi>Papacy</hi> it ſelf, hath no better ground, I mean their Popes <hi>Supremacy,</hi> as St. <hi>Peters</hi> pretended Succeſſor, is nothing but dream and Phanſie; or which is worſe, affected Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance and Preſumption, or precarious and violent <hi>Impoſition</hi> upon the Chriſtian World; becauſe they found it abſolutely neceſſary for the ſupport of a rotten or unſound Building. And being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help, either of Scripture or found Reaſon it reſts only upon, and reſolves at laſt, into a feined <hi>Will</hi> of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that was never proved <hi>per teſtes,</hi> by lawful Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſs the <hi>Papacy</hi> is <hi>Fanatical</hi> from top to bottom; but how doth it appear, that <hi>Sooinianiſm</hi> is ſo. This is the next enquiry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. Fanaticiſm <hi>at the bottom of</hi> Socinianiſm.</head>
               <p>TO be clear in this enquiry, we muſt conſider the <hi>Fundamental</hi> point, on which the <hi>Socinian</hi> Religion as ſuch, chiefly if not entirely reſts, and from whence it ariſeth: and 'tis plainly this, whether our <hi>Saviour had a being before he was born of the Virgin</hi> Mary: On this, hang all the great queſtions, touching our Lords <hi>Filiation, Natures, Divinity, Merit, Satisfaction</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion;</hi> and are decided and determined, as that ſtands or falls.</p>
               <p>Now, this great point, <hi>Whether our Saviour had a being before he was born of the Virgin,</hi> hath an eſſential dependance on another, which of abſolute neceſſity muſt be evinced before, in order to the determination of this, and therefore this other point lies deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the <hi>Foundation,</hi> ſeeing upon it depends that Reſolution, <hi>whether our Saviour had a being before he was born of the Virgin or no;</hi> and that is, whether our Saviour had a <hi>Being with his Father in Heaven before</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106798:17"/> he was born of the Virgin, or whether he had not been in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before, but aſcended or was taken up thither only, after he was ſo born and had been ſometime in the Fleſh.</p>
               <p>Now, the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> abounding with ſo many plain proofs that our Saviour <hi>came down from Heaven</hi> (Nine or Ten times aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in that one Chapter, the Sixth of St. <hi>John) Socinus</hi> and his Followers dare not, do not deny it. But 'tis ſo eſſential to their Religion, to deny that our Saviour had any Being before he was Born of the Virgin, and in conſequence, to ſupport their whole <hi>Fabrick</hi> upon this <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> they at laſt found out a <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> to reconcile the contradiction; tho' at firſt they had diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Notions and did heſitate about it, yet at laſt they ſeem to agree, and do now <hi>unanimouſly</hi> affirm; that after our <hi>Saviour</hi> was born of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> he <hi>was taken up into Heaven;</hi> and then coming down again, he is ſaid to <hi>come down from Heaven</hi> ſo often, in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>Then this is the very <hi>Root,</hi> Foundation, and Corner Stone, upon which <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> is framed and ſupported, that <hi>our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour after he was born of the Virgin was taken up</hi> (in the Fleſh) <hi>into Heaven,</hi> to receive inſtructions from his Father for the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Mankind.</p>
               <p>Now (to apply to our purpoſe) if this great point, upon <note place="margin">Application<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> which <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> ſo intirely depends, have no <hi>Foundation,</hi> either in the <hi>Word</hi> of God or ſound <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and be founded only in <hi>Dream</hi> or <hi>Phanſie,</hi> or preſumptive Invention to ſave the <hi>Fabrick,</hi> their great <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> from ſinking; or rather in pretended <hi>Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> or Revelation; is not <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> as truly <hi>Phanatical</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſtical,</hi> as the <hi>Papacy;</hi> not to ſay <hi>Mahomatiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they are ſo daring as to affirm, 'tis to be found in the <note place="margin">Not in Scripture.</note> 
                  <hi>Scripture;</hi> they ought to be ſo kind to us, and ſo juſt to their Cauſe, as to ſhew us <hi>where:</hi> They ſeem to make us ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of our Lords <hi>Aſſention</hi> into Heaven as a Man, in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s being in the <hi>Mount</hi> with God; and St. <hi>Pauls Rapture</hi> into the third Heaven, but it was St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Moſes;</hi> where do we find any ſuch thing ſaid of Chriſt, unleſs it were upon Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> but that will not ſerve their purpoſe.</p>
               <p>'Tis plain our Lord came down from <hi>Heaven:</hi> Our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is certain, that he was there: And the Text is evident, that he came down from Heaven before he is ſaid to have <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended:</hi> And he that came down from Heaven, and was on Earth, in his <hi>Humanity,</hi> was ſtill equally in Heaven, in his <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity:</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106798:18"/> all this is plain <hi>Scripture,</hi> John 3. 13. <hi>No Man hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended up into Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven; even the Son of Man which is in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But where are we told that our Lord in <hi>Fleſh</hi> aſcended up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven and then came down again? Certainly, if this be the Truth that muſt ſupport ſo much of Religion, 'twould have been recorded ſomewhere in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and not have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Silence and Myſtery.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially, ſeeing the <hi>Socinians</hi> themſelves obſerve, (even with boaſting;) the <hi>Fulneſs,</hi> as well as the <hi>Clearneſs</hi> of thoſe Holy Writings with reſpect to every thing <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be believed; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks their own great Reaſon ſhould force them to confeſs, that ſo great a point, ought not to be believed by themſelves, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded upon the World, ſeeing it is no <hi>where</hi> to be found in thoſe Sacred Books.</p>
               <p>That 'tis not to be found therein, appears evidently by ſome obſervations touching the difference among the <hi>Socinians</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and the difficulties they encounter'd with before they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be ſatisfied about it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> They began to play with the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as they uſe to do in other matters; and pretended a ſtrange diſcovery of a <hi>Figurative</hi> Sence; and interpreted our Saviours being in Heaven, either by his Heavenly <hi>Meditations</hi> or Divine <hi>Knowledge:</hi> But when he came down, did he leave behind him his ſuch Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Knowledge? This <hi>Non-ſence Socinus</hi> was ſoon aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of, and came to this Reſolution; that our Saviour, after he was in the Fleſh, did aſcend in <hi>Perſon</hi> into Heaven; but upon the <hi>Time</hi> when he did ſo, he and his Followers were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> This is the Second difficulty, wherein they were plunged; that upon a ſuppoſition, that Chriſt was taken up into Heaven, when it ſhould be. Some of them ſay, it was, when he was Twelve Years Old, and <hi>when his Parents miſſed him,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">As <hi>Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>zog. Schilict. Crellius.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>after three days found him amongſt the Doctors:</hi> Others of great name amongſt them, ſuppoſe it was, during his <hi>being For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days in the Wilderneſs,</hi> and this now ſeems to be the general and current Opinion with them: But do theſe Texts ſay any thing elſe, but that our Saviour was in the <hi>Temple</hi> when his Parents ſought him; and that he was in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> tempted of the <hi>Devil</hi> (an odd diſcription of Heaven?) theſe places of Scripture then will not do. Have they any other? We hear
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106798:18"/> of no other: and therefore, we may be bold to conclude, there is no ground in <hi>Scripture</hi> for that great <hi>Point,</hi> that is the <hi>Baſis</hi> of <hi>Socinian</hi> Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Neither in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> For if it be not <hi>Revealed</hi> in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Not in Reaſon.</note> 'tis beyond the <hi>Ken</hi> of the moſt Sagacious, without a good Invention, to make a Diſcovery of it, for that which can be known only by Revelation, can certainly be known no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; but none can poſſibly imagine (not the moſt phanſiful <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian)</hi> how this matter of <hi>Fact</hi> could ever fall under the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal underſtanding of any Man, except it were revealed from Heaven. If Reaſon could diſcover ſome plauſible colour, <hi>Why</hi> our Lord ſhould be taken up into Heaven before his paſſion, yet certainly, <hi>That</hi> he was ſo, is matter of pure Revelation, and not to be known otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>We muſt conclude alſo, that this their great principle hath no more foundation in ſound Reaſon, then in the <hi>Holy Scripture:</hi> That is, none at all. 'Tis unſcriptural, and no reaſon can be given for it, but the neceſſity of it to ſupport an <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> that falls with it, or without it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly and Laſtly,</hi> To ſhut up all, 'Tis not only not founded ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fanatick</hi> and <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical.</hi>
                  </note> in <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and ſo <hi>Fanatical</hi> enough; but 'tis pure <hi>Enthuſiaſm,</hi> even by their own Confeſſion. How much <hi>Faſting,</hi> how much <hi>Study,</hi> what earneſt <hi>Prayers</hi> to Almighty God, did <hi>Laelius Socinus</hi> pay for this rare great and notable Diſcovery? But was it any more then Dream and Phanſie (if it deſerve not a worſe name) tho' it commenced <hi>Enthuſiaſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall end with that ſmart and pertinent Reflection of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Learned <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> in his late excellent Treatiſe of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity, p.</hi> 143. Speaking of this <hi>Text,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt came down from Heaven. Did</hi> Socinus, ſaith he, <hi>find it ſo eaſie a matter to reconcile this Text to his darling Opinion, when he was fain to faſt and pray for it; and pretend Revelation, becauſe he wanted Reaſon to ſupport it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Merciful GOD who haſt made all Men, and hateſt nothing that thou haſt made, nor wouldeſt the death of a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but rather that he ſhould be Converted and live; have Mercy upon all</hi> Jews, Turks, Infidels, <hi>and</hi> Heriticks, <hi>and take from them all Ignorance, hardneſs of Heart, and contempt</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106798:19"/> 
                  <hi>of thy Word, and ſo fetch them home Bleſſed Lord to thy Flock, that they may be ſaved among the Remnant of the true</hi> Iſraelites, <hi>and be made one Fold under one Shepheard, JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST our Lord, who liveth and Reigneth with Thee and the Holy Spirit, One God, World without End.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:106798:19"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
